A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of John S. Nagel FA719
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, International Division, Office Files of John S. Nagel
1966-1975
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
FA719
1.32 Cubic Feet
The International Division Papers of John S. Nagel document his activities and a number of those of the International Division's Latin America and Caribbean (ID/LAC) office for the period 1966 to 1975. The papers were accessioned into the Archives in two stages: Series I, Population Files, 1966-1972, were transferred to the Archives in February 1982; Series II, Correspondence Files, 1968-1975, were removed from terminated office files shipped to New York for permanent storage from the Mexico City field office in March 1978. These papers consist of copies of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. Arrangement within each series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Nagel's New York and Mexico City offices.
Conditions Governing Access
Material more than ten years old is open for research. Select individual files are restricted, as noted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Separated Materials
Staff and consultant reports and publications have been pulled and accessioned into the FF Archives. A cross-reference sheet located within the folders denotes accessioned reports. A list of titles removed from the papers is appended to this register. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Biographical / Historical
John S. Nagel, Ford Foundation Program Advisor in Population for the Latin America and Caribbean office (LAC) of the International Division, was a member of the Foundation staff from 1962 until his retirement in 1977. During this period, he held the following positions:
April 1973, Program Advisor, LAC, Mexico City, ID
September 1968, Deputy and Program Officer, LAC, New York, ID
June 1966, Representative, LAC, Argentina, ID
June 1965, Representative, LAC, Argentina and Chile, OD
July 1962, Representative, LAC, Mexico and Central America, Mexico City, OD
January 1962, Associate Director, LAC, New York, OD
Mr. Nagel also served as a consultant to the Ford Foundation on two separate occassions following his retirement. From June 1977 until December 1978, he monitored and evaluated program activities in the field of population for the LAC office; and from November 1979 until September 1980, he served in the Population Program on communications projects.
John Nagel was born June 5, 1913. He received his B.S. degree in Commerce from Northwestern University in 1934.
Prior to Nagel's career with the Ford Foundation, he held the following positions:
1953-1961, Needham, Louis and Brorby, Director of Marketing; V.P. and Account Supervisor
1948-1953, Young and Rubicam, Marketing and Account Executive
1943-1948, Booz, Allen and Hamilton, Staff Manager and Director of Executive Personnel Recruitment
1941-1943, Zurich Insurance, Sales Promotion Manager and Assistant Director of Public Relations
1936-1941, Northwestern University, Director of Alumni Relations and Assistant to Vice President in Charge of Production
After his retirement and consultantcies with the Foundation, Mr. Nagel moved to Naples, Florida.
Scope and Contents
The three boxes of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports which constitute the International Division Papers of John S. Nagel, document his activities and a number of those of the Foundation's Latin America and Caribbean (LAC) office for the years 1966 to 1975.
The papers, which are broad in scope, yet lacking in quantity and depth, contain material on Foundation sponsored population projects including the Bellagio Population Group; the International Agency for Contraceptive Research and Development; the International Planned Parenthood Federation; and the Pan American Health Organization. The material consists of reports and related correspondence. The papers are indicative of the role Nagel played within the Latin America and Caribbean program.
The correspondence files document the day-to-day program activity and other Foundation related correspondence of Nagel for the period 1966 to 1975.
Arrangement
The International Division Papers of John S. Nagel are divided into two series:
I. Population Files, 1966-1972
II. Chronological Files, 1968-1975
- Population Files, 1966-1972; I
  Arrangement
  Series I, Population Files (1966-1972), is the most substantive. It contains population files arranged in alphabetical order by subject. Printed matter consists of correspondence, inter-office memoranda, and reports. Within each folder, the files are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - ACORD - International Agency for Contraceptive Research and Development, 1969 December-1970 May (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bellagio Population Group, 1969 July-1971 July (Box 1, Folder 2-5)
  - Ford Foundation Program in Reproductive Biology, 1972 January (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Inter-American Development Bank, 1969 November-1971 March (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - International Planned Parenthood Federation, 1969 September-1971 May (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Nutrition, 1970 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - OAS - PAHO, 1969 February-1970 May (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Population Advisor Mailings, 1971 December-1972 September (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Population Council, 1969 April-1970 June (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Population Strategy - Trustees, 1970 July-November (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - University of California, 1968 August (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - University of Chicago, 1966 February-1971 June (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - University of Michigan, 1967 December-1969 January (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - UNC Population Center, 1969 May-1970 October (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Chronological Files, 1968-1975; II
  Series II, Chronological Files (1968-1975), is the most extensive. It contains two subject files and copies of Nagel's outgoing correspondence and inter-office memoranda with FF colleagues, grantee organizations, and individuals and oraganizations seeking grants. The files are arranged in reverse calendar order. Within each folder, the papers are arranged in reverse chronological order.
  - Grant Action Guidelines, 1972 June-November (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Legal Basis for Overseas Activities, 1970 September-November (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - 1975 April-May (Box 2, Folder 20-21)
  - 1974 February (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23-34)
  - 1972 (Box 2, Folder 35-46)
  - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 47-58)
  - 1970 (Box 3, Folder 59-70)
  - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 71-81)
  - 1968 (Box 3, Folder 82-87)